Alright, okay, so, okay, okay, so, I don't know, maybe, it's
difficult. Today's דף daf is יוד, yud, and we start with the
משנה, mishna, and now we suddenly move onto something a lot easier
than פתחי נדה pitchay nida and the months of the year. That
was hard. Right? Yeah. You should've tried to do the רש"י Rashi
and תוספות. Tosfos. Anyway, let's take a look now at the משנה,
mishna, much much easier discussion and also quite relevant, and I hope
you'll be surprised to see once again how relevant ערכין Arachin is
to so many issues. Let's take a look at the משנה. mishna.
אין פוחתין מעשרים ואחת
תקיעות במקדש. Ein pochtin me-esrim v'achas tki'os bamiktash. Okay, this is not
yet the relevant part. They would have no fewer than 21 blasts
in the מקדש. mikdash. This is not שופר shofar blasts, but חצוצרות
chatzotzros blasts. When was they? Well, I'll tell you in a minute.
ולא מוסיפין על ארבעים ושמונה. V'lo mosifin al arba'im ushmona. Not more
than 48. So what would this be? So the first thing to
know is that everything comes in a set of three: תקיעה, תרועה,
תקיעה. teki'a tru'a teki'a So basically it is 7 sets between 7
sets and 16 sets. Okay, so I'll just use those numbers because
it'll make it easier to keep track. So what are the standard
seven sets of תקיעה, תרועה, תקיעה? tekiah teruah tekiah So you do
number one when you basically open the gates when the day begins.
You do a three at the bringing of the תמיד של שחר.
tamid shel shachar. There are three times
that the לויים Levi'im interrupt their song and there's a break in
the song and you do תקיעה, תרועה, tekiah teruah. תקיעות. tki'os. And
you do three in the תמיד של בין הערביים. tamid shel bein
ha'arbayim. Okay, so those are the communal sacrifices of any day and
the opening of the gates, that's your standard seven. Again, 21, but
we're talking about them as sets. How do you get to more?
ערב שבת Erev Shabbos you would have two sets. One would be
to, you know, sort of like our 18 minutes to tell the
people to announce that שבת Shabbos is about to arrive and give
them time to wrap up everything they're doing and come back from
the field. And then another one at the exact beginning of שבת.
Shabbos. So that's two more sets, now we're up to nine sets.
On a יום טוב Yom Tov where there's a קרבן מוסף, korban
musaf, you do another three, so up to 12.
Oh, and this was ערב שבת Erev Shabbos and so
now if you have ערב שבת Erev Shabbos that's also יום טוב,
Yom Tov, right, because you have to stop more מלאכה melacha from
יום טוב Yom Tov going into שבת Shabbos so you still do
those blasts on ערב שבת Erev Shabbos on a יום טוב Yom
Tov leading into שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so now you're up to 12.
Now on
סוכות Succos where you had the special ritual
of ניסוך המים, nisuch hamayim, which was accompanied with שופר shofar blasts,
they would do one set when they open the upper gate because
they would go down in procession from the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
to fill up the water, one when they would open the lower
gate, one when they would fill it up with the water, and
one when they would actually pour the water on the מזבח, mizbeiach,
and that gives you four more. So an ערב שבת Erev Shabbos
which is סוכות Succos and that's going to give you 16 sets,
48 blasts. Okay. ולא מוס, V'lo mos, that's the first line of
the משנה. mishna. All that is discussed in משנה mishna in סוכה
Succah that's spelled out in the משנה. mishna. אין פוחתין משני נבלים,
Ein pochtin mishnei nevalim, נבלים, nevalim, נבלים, nevalim, excuse me,
נבלים, nevalim, נבלים nevalim I guess would be a נבלה nevalah but
that would be נבלות. nevelot. Anyway, נבלים nevalim ולא מוסיפין על ששה.
v'lo mosifin al shisha. You have no fewer in the musical instruments
that accompany the singing. The עיקר ikar thing that the לויים Levi'im
did was not the instruments but the song. עיקר שירה בפה, Ikar
shirah b'peh, the גמרא Gemara says. And we're actually going to see
in a minute who did the musical instruments. But there would be
no fewer than two lyres and harps like little harps and no
more than six. רש"י Rashi actually says: לא נתפרש טעמא, Lo nitparesh
ta'ama, he does not know why, which is interesting. Do you know
what it says elsewhere? I don't think תוספות Tosfos suggests anything. Anyway,
אין פוחתין משני חלילין, Ein pochtin mishnei chalilin, there would be no
fewer than two flutes, ולא מוסיפין על שנים עשר. v'lo mosifin al
shneim asar. Not more than 12. רש"י Rashi says the reason of
not more than 12 is because we're about to see in the
משנה mishna which is going to be the focus of the גמרא's
Gemara discussion that there were 12 days in particular where they would
play the flute, which is actually the next line. Now רש"י Rashi
says they would never use the flute on any other day except
these 12. The רמב"ם Rambam actually, even though they would have all
these other musical instruments, the harp and the cymbals and all these
things, the flute would be dedicated basically we'll see to pretty much
יום טוב Yom Tov days, or we'll see exactly what those days
are, to distinguish them. But anyway the רש"י Rashi says they wouldn't
even play it on the other days. רמב"ם Rambam indicates they would
play it on the other days, but maybe
they would be solos on the following days. So let's take a
look. ובשנים עשר יום בשנה, Ubishneim asar yom bashanah,
there were 12 special days in the year, החליל מכה לפני המזבח,
hachalil makeh lifnei hamizbeiach, that you would have the flute playing in
front of the altar. The reason it uses the word מכה, makeh,
רש"י Rashi says, is because you would tap with your fingers over
the holes, so that's referred to as מכה, makeh, the sort of
the playing of the flute, the tapping of the finger. Okay, so
there would be 12 special days that would be that the focus
of the or the only instrument that would play that exactly clear,
but let's say it means the only... The instrument that would play
would be the flute. Now what were those twelve days? Let's take
a look.
שחיטת הפסח ראשון ושחיטת הפסח שני, Shchitat hapesach rishon v'shchitat hapesach sheini,
the bringing of the קרבן korban of the קרבן פסח korban pesach
of פסח ראשון Pesach rishon and פסח שני, Pesach sheini, ויום טוב
הראשון של פסח, v'yomtov harishon shel pesach, the first day of פסח,
Pesach, because the bringing of the קרבן פסח korban pesach was the
14th of ניסן Nisan and the first day of פסח. Pesach. וביום
טוב של עצרת, u'viyomtov shel atzeret, שבועות, Shavuot, that's actually interesting. You
don't have to say יום טוב של עצרת. yomtov shel atzeret. You
have to say יום טוב של פסח, yomtov shel pesach, you have
to say יום טוב של סוכות, yomtov shel sukkot, but you don't
have to say יום טוב של עצרת yomtov shel atzeret because it's
only one day of שבועות. Shavuot. You also don't have to say
יום טוב של ראש השנה. yomtov shel rosh hashanah. But the משנה
Mishnah does say יום טוב של עצרת, yomtov shel atzeret, יום טוב
של ראש השנה yomtov shel rosh hashanah because that's just the phrase
because it's also used particularly when there's a חול המועד chol hamoed
to highlight that it's יום טוב yomtov or underscore it anyway. So
on the first day of פסח, Pesach, on שבועות, Shavuot, ובשמונת ימי
החג u'vishmonat yemei hachag and the eight days of סוכות. Sukkot. So
that's eight, one, and one is ten for the שלוש רגלים shalosh
regalim and the two bringings of the קרבן פסח korban pesach is
twelve. Now bracketing the two bringings of the קרבן פסח, korban pesach,
is there anything
that rings a bell, that idea of פסח, Pesach, the first day
of פסח, Pesach, שבועות, Shavuot, and the eight days of סוכות? Sukkot?
They are the same as הלל. Hallel. The obvious question is why
only the first day of פסח Pesach and why all eight days
of סוכות? Sukkot?
And not the last day of פסח Pesach you mean.
And not all eight days of פסח.
Pesach. No because סוכות Sukkot is a
קרבן חלוקין. korban chalukin. I mean קרבנות חלוקין korbanot chalukin I meant
to say.
All right so that's what I was going to say. But anyway
the point is you might that it's hard we maybe it's not
high in our sort of recognition, but those are basically the distinctions
between when you say a full הלל Hallel and a חצי הלל.
chatzi Hallel. Bracketing חנוכה, Chanukah, but if you know you say a
full הלל Hallel on every day of סוכות Sukkot but only on
the first day of פסח, Pesach, and the גמרא Gemara is going
to connect the two. But the משנה, Mishnah, that is really like
the key question. Why this and why not ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and why every day of סוכות Sukkot
and not every day of פסח, Pesach, and why the days you
bring קרבן פסח? korban pesach? Anyway we will see, but these are
obviously very special days and the way they were distinguished was with
the playing of the flute. And that's going to be this is
going to be one of the key גמרות Gemaros that relate to
the saying of הלל Hallel because the גמרא Gemara is going to
make the connection although the משנה Mishnah does not. Let's take a
look. Now just back to some of the practice of how it
was done. ולא היה מכה באבוב של נחושת, V'lo haya makkeh be'abuv
shel nechoshet, they would not use a copper flute אלא באבוב של
קנה, ella be'abuv shel kaneh, a reed one, מפני שקולו ערב, mipnei
she'kolo areiv, for no other reason than it produced a more beautiful
mellifluous sound than the metal one.
More than a silver one?
ולא היה
מחליט V'lo haya machlit or מחליט machleit אלא באבוב יחידי. ella be'abuv
yachidi. רש"י Rashi says it means sort of like end the playing
except with a flute solo. So although they might have had twelve
flutes playing,
the coda, the little the way in the end that it sort
of gets closure and wraps up would be with a solo.
This idea only the כהנים Kohanim played?
Well
it was by the I mean there were ישראלים Yisraelim that were
pretty close by. They were like twenty feet away. Like the ישראל
Yisrael could stand right in an area, a small area of about
fifteen feet, a strip very long but very narrow, fifteen feet right
in front of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, not right up to. But
there must have been
animals being killed right there.
That's a good question. I mean look, maybe when these were the
special it's also not exactly spelled out at which קרבן korban was
this done. Was this done
at there definitely
was the special playing of the flute that was done on these
days, it stands to reason it was done only at the קרבן
מוסף korban musaf or whether it was קרבן פסח. korban pesach. So
anyway the קרבן מוסף, korban musaf, maybe they maybe it was a
very maybe everything else was quieted down. They were bringing the one
קרבן מוסף. korban musaf. But קרבן פסח, korban pesach, you're absolutely right.
Because the קרבן פסח korban pesach was a madhouse. It was a
total madhouse, the קרבן פסח. korban pesach. So you're right about that.
Anyway it would end with a flute solo מפני שהוא מחליט יפה
mipnei she'hu machlit yafeh
because that is a nice way to end it by doing a
flute solo. Now who would play the musical instruments? This presumably is
not limiting itself to the question of the flute, but whenever there
would be musical instruments. And it's not necessarily the לויים Levi'im because
the עיקר שירה בפה, ikar shirah b'peh, the primary musical accompaniment for
the קרבנות korbanot is understood to be what they their singing. The
instruments are just the accompaniment to the singing. So that does not
have to be limited to the לויים. Levi'im. So who would do
it? ועבדי כהנים היו. V'avdei kohanim hayu. Look at that. It was
not even it was ועבדי כהנים, avdei kohanim, it was the slaves
of the כהנים. Kohanim. So it was still within the כהנים Kohanim
family.
They were allowed in? Apparently because you know on the one hand
they're considered as sort of part of the כהנים Kohanim family, they
eat תרומה. terumah. But normally the reason they're seen as part of
the כהנים Kohanim family has a little more to do with seeing
them as like property.
So that's like a shocking statement that it would be
ועבדי כהנים.
avdei kohanim. Does ר' מאיר Rebbi Meir say anything?
Well we're going
to see
it's not that ישראלים Yisraelim can't.
Actually
it was these two families, Israel families, that the family of Pagrim
or Pagris and Tzipara that were from this place called Ammaum or
Ammaus and they were had very good יחוס. yichus. So כהנים Kohanim
would marry into those families, but nevertheless they were Israel. So basically
the two these two answers are saying people you would never imagine
would have a function in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but because
somehow they were part of the periphery and they were associated with
כהנים, Kohanim, either their slaves or people that they, you know, יחוס
yichus families they would intermarry with close to כהנים, Kohanim, they would
actually play the musical instruments. Wait, all of them or just some
of them? The ones that had the musical ability. Some oh, presumably
all.
But the daughters of the כהנים Kohanim would marry the men, right?
No.
So
משיאין לכהונה, mesi'in li-khuna, usually משיאין לכהונה mesi'in li-khuna means the כהנים
Kohanim would marry their daughters.
But the daughters wouldn't play the flute.
Right, but the family was מיוחס. meyuchas. So so you know but
so who
was playing the flute?
The men. Right. But no, the assumption is that you come from
a very no, no, no. Men כהנים Kohanim would marry daughters from
these families. So the men of those families, not the married-in כהנים,
Kohanim, the brothers of these women that the כהנים Kohanim would marry.
That doesn't seem to be what it
that's the assumption I'm saying.
Not the brother but
look not every family it's the
point that כהנים Kohanim would marry in doesn't mean every single girl
from that family was married to a כהן. Kohen. It just means
they came from a very they were Rothschilds, okay? So all the
כהנים Kohanim wanted to marry Rothschild girls, okay?
So what does that have to do with the players?
It just means it's like the same like the slaves of the
כהנים. Kohanim. These were families, these were people that were close to
the כהנים. Kohanim.
So because your brother-in-law or maybe
your brother-in-law's sister's player,
he's allowed to come where only כהנים Kohanim could come to play
something that right, I understand it's the same question about the slaves.
Now it's not telling you where they stood, okay, which is an
interesting question. They stood on the מזבח? mizbe'ach? Right, but I'm saying
there's a whole area לפני המזבח. lifnei ha-mizbe'ach. You have to see
it
still the inner I understand, I understand.
But I'm saying it's not more shocking than the slaves. Slaves are
people you would never imagine would play a role. Right.
No, but the slave is part
the slave is always has a lower status than a free person.
So right, I understand. I understand.
Right, so you're right, so it's not because they are seen as
part directly part of כהנים Kohanim household. These are seen as just
as just, you know, well-standing,
you know, Israelite families and so the question is I think the
question is is משיאין לכהונה mesi'in li-khuna just a proof that they're
good יחוס yichus families and really the point is that they just
have good יחוס yichus or is משיאין לכהונה mesi'in li-khuna the point
the way I was trying to frame it which is what you're
reacting to, make them more like associated with כהנים. Kohanim. And if
you take that approach then you're phrasing it how associated are they.
Okay, I hear that. Alright. רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס אומר לויים היו.
Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos omer Levi'im hayu. No,
no, no, they're לויים Levi'im did this as well. Let's not assume
that it was non-לויים. Levi'im. So here's a fascinating just very simple
factual question: who were the music players? Right? I wonder if they've
if they've resolved that at any degree with any archaeology that they've
done to figure out who were the people that were the musical
players.
And is there any reason that a woman couldn't play the חליל
chalil up there?
Right, I mean these are just seen as accompaniment. They're not seen
as the עבודה. avoda. If an if an עבד eved could, yeah,
I don't know, that's a very good question.
I would assume according to right,
I would certainly assume according to the opinion that an עבד eved
could I would certainly assume that a woman could. Right, I'll have
to look into it. That's a very, very good question. But it's
not indicating the
brother-in-law of the I understand.
No, but when they say it's a family from which they would
take women it does not mean that we're focusing on the women,
we're focusing on the family. But I certainly think that the question
about women once you're not limiting it to כהנים Kohanim and לויים
Levi'im and you're even extending it to עבדים avadim and Israelite families,
right,
it's a very good question. Let me see if I can find
some material on that.
So we'll say just briefly is that, you know, you would have
thought either having no more than this number of players, no more
than those number of players, you would have thought that, you know,
they'd have a a whole orchestra and the more the better, the
more, you know
yeah, but if they're not supposed to overshadow the singers
well, you can always alternate, you know, you can have like a
I don't know,
harmony and then like you know what I mean?
I don't know. Okay, let's I have no answer. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. So first we look at the number
of תקיעות. teki'os. Remember in order to count them I simplified it
by grouping them as threes. But the משנה Mishna doesn't group them
in threes. It says anywhere between, you know, twenty-one and forty-eight. So
the גמרא Gemara says מתניתין דלא כרבי יהודה. masnisin d'lo ke-Rabbi Yehuda.
That counting each blast separately is not like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
דתניא di-tanya a
ברייתא, beraita, רבי יהודה אומר הפוחת לא יפחות משבע והמוסיף לא יוסיף
על שש עשרה. Rabbi Yehuda omer ha-poches lo yifchos mi-sheva ve-ha-mosif lo
yosif al sheish esrei. Not more than sixteen. So it's basically what
I said, right? It's basically the same as twenty-one and forty-eight except
he's counting תקיעה תרועה תקיעה tekiah teruah tekiah as one unit. So
the גמרא Gemara Says that it sounds like that there's some real
debate here whether conceptually תקיעה תרועה תקיעה tekiah teruah tekiah is one
unit or three units, and there might have and there are halakhic
implications. So let's take a look. במאי קמיפלגי, be-mai ka-miflagi, what's the
dispute about?
רבי יהודה סבר Rabbi Yehuda savar תקיעה tki'a, תרועה תקיעה teruah tekiah.
חדא היא, chada hi, tekiah teruah tekiah counts as one unit.
ורבנן סברי ve-rabbanan savri תקיעה לחודיה ותרועה לחודיה, tekiah l'chudei u-teruah l'chudei,
they're separate units, ותקיעה לחודיה ve-tekiah l'chudei and each one of those
three is a separate unit. Okay, so מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה, mai
ta'ama de-Rabbi Yehuda, what's the reasoning of Rabbi Yehuda that conceptually calls
it one
blast? כתיב ותקעתם תרועה, ktiv u-tekatem teruah, you shall blow a teruah.
It doesn't say והרעותם תרועה. ve-hareiotem teruah. The verb is תקיעה tki'a.
although it's referring to a תרועה. tru'a, וכתיב תרועה יתקעו, u-ktiv teruah
yitkau, another verse says you should be tokeia a teruah. So the
fact that it uses the verb for one for the noun of
the other shows that basically you see these all as connecting as
one type of one type of blast that has those different components
to it. But if they were really conceptually separate units, you would
use different verbs for them as well. ורבנן, ve-rabbanan,
that's what he does. ורבנן סברי ve-rabbanan savri no, that just tells
you, I'm sorry did I skip a line? שמע מינה תקיעה ותרועה
ותקיעה חדא היא, shema mina tekiah u-teruah u-tekiah chada hi, and you
see that they're all one. And also we're about to see in
a minute that that's how you learn out you do tekiah teruah
tekiah. ורבנן ve-rabbanan and the Rabbis say, no, it's not to tell
you it's one. It's to tell you that that's the blasts you
do. ההוא לפשוטה לפניה ופשוטה לאחריה הוא דאתא. hahu le-pshuta lefaneha u-pshuta
leachareha hu de-ata. That's coming just to tell you that you do
a tekiah before and a tekiah after. How do you get it?
דכתיב ותקעתם תרועה, de-chtiv u-tekatem teruah, we read it not just as
a verb, but we read it as תקיעה tki'a, תרועה. tru'a, And
then the other verse
says תרועה יתקעו, teruah yitkau, so we read it as תרועה tru'a,
תקיעה. tki'a? So from there we learn that with every teruah a
tekiah has to precede
and a tekiah has to follow. So yes, we do learn out
that tekiah comes before and after a teruah, but we don't learn
that it's considered one unit. ורבי יהודה ve-Rabbi Yehuda says, once we're
learning that out, tekiah teruah tekiah, and we're learning it from the
mixing of the verb with the noun, then it is telling me
that it's one unit. So that's exactly the debate.
And you don't need two teruahs like tekiah teruah teruah tekiah?
That's the דרשה drasha is because fundamentally you need a תרועה, teruah.
and we learn from these פסוקים psukim that whenever you have a
teruah it has to be preceded and followed with a tekiah. The
teruah is the focus. Yes, that's conceptually what we're saying. The teruah
is the focus, but the tekiah comes before and after. And the
only debate is that since the verb is sort of intermingling it,
is it telling you that it's one unit or not? Okay, ורבנן
מאי טעמא, ve-rabbanan mai ta'ama, so where do the Rabbis get the
idea that it's separate units? דכתיב ובהקהיל
את הקהל תתקעו ולא תריעו. de-chtiv u-ve-hak-hil et ha-kahal titke'u ve-lo tari'u.
We have times where a tekiah comes by itself, right? When you
do the things associated with the קרבנות, korbanot, as Michael was pointing
out was implicit, the emphasis is the teruah, right? What does it
say? It says וביום שמחתכם
ובמועדיכם ובראשי חדשיכם והרעותם בחצצרות. u-ve-yom simchatchem u-ve-moadechem u-ve-rashei chodsheichem ve-hareiotem ba-chatzotzrot.
Right there it actually uses the verb והרעותם, ve-hareiotem, which is teruah.
So by korbanot the עיקר ikar is teruah. Okay, but the psukim
say, this is by the חצוצרות chatzotzrot not the שופר, shofar, that
when you're just gathering the camp, there it's the tekiah is the
עיקר. ikar. Okay, so when you're doing korbanot, the focus is the
teruah, but every teruah is preceded and followed with a tekiah. That's
how you get that. When you're gathering the camps, you just do
a tekiah. Now the Rabbis say, look, if you can have a
tekiah by itself, it proves that a tekiah is a distinct sound
from the teruah or distinct unit from the teruah, because you're having
otherwise who would say do half a sound? So if you do
it by itself, clearly it's considered to be a whole sound by
itself. דאי סלקא דעתך de-i salka dach-tach תקיעה תרועה ותקיעה חדא היא,
tekiah teruah u-tekiah chada hi, if that's considered just one sound, tekiah
teruah tekiah, so אמר רחמנא עביד פלגא דמצוה, amar rachmana avid palga
de-mitzvah, the Torah would say do half of the mitzvah, half of
a sound? סבר רבי יהודה, savar Rabbi Yehuda, Rabbi Yehuda would say
back, סימנא בעלמא הוא. simana b'alma hu. No, that's not really a
mitzvah. That's just a way to gather people. It's like standing up
and yelling, hey guys, let's all get together! So it doesn't have
to be a formal halakhic sound, and a tekiah is enough. But
when you are talking about something which is more ritualized, not just
a loudspeaker, but a ritual, there tekiah teruah tekiah is a unit
with conceptually everybody agrees teruah is the ikar, but he would say
that that's one indivisible unit. Now the Gemara is going to spell
out what a possible נפקא מינה nafka mina is. We have yet
to deal with a nafka mina. So the Gemara says, כמאן אזלא
הא דאמר ke-man azla ha de-amar who is this going like that
which says רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, אין בין תקיעה לתרועה ולא כלום,
ein bein tekiah le-teruah ve-lo klum, you cannot have any interruption between
tekiah teruah, you can't even pause for a millisecond. So you have
to one has to flow into the next? Right, all basically in
one breath. Who is that going like? כמאן? ke-man? לרבי יהודה, le-Rabbi
Yehuda, like Rabbi Yehuda. So there you go, that's a simple nafka
mina. If you call it one sound, then you can't make breaks
between it. It has to be one sound that starts with a
tekiah, moves into a teruah, and ends with a tekiah. And all
of that has to be one sound. And that's
Rabbi Yehuda. פשיטא, pshita, of course it's Rabbi Yehuda. Who else
would
it be? they have to be one sound. What does it mean
that you don't interrupt? It means the following: לפוקי מדרבי יוחנן, lifokei
mid’Rabbi Yochanan, to, in order to reject the position of רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, דאמר רבי יוחנן, d’amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says by the, now we’re shifting to the תקיעות תרועות tekios teruos
of ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, שמע תשע תקיעות בתשע שעות ביום יצא.
shama tisha tekiyot betisha shaot bayom yatza. Even if you heard a
תקיעה tki'a, at 6:00 a.m., a תרועה teruah, at 7:00, another תקיעה
tekiah at 8:00, another תקיעה tekiah at 9:00, then a תרועה teruah
at 10:00, you heard your nine, nine blasts, right? Really there’s only
nine blasts that are required on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, we just
don’t know which, what's תרועה, teruah so it becomes twenty-seven, which is
thirty. Anyway, we won’t go through all of that. But he says
if you knew which nine, you could do one each hour and
be יוצא. yotzei. You could have a huge break between them. So,
this, so that, you don’t have to call it one sound to
say you can't have a big break, right? It still could be
a unit, not a unit, it could still be like a, what
would you call it? Like a group without being a unit, without
being a single sound. So maybe all we mean to do is
reject that position. So, so therefore, קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan,
that he's telling me that when we say there can't be any
interruption, we're not just saying you can't hear them in nine separate
hours, we're going even further, we're saying that there has to be
not even a breath between them, it literally has to be one
sound. ואימא הכי נמי, ve’eima hachi nami, and how do you know?
Maybe it really is just saying what you said, that you can’t
have big gaps. No. ואימא הכי נמי. ve’eima hachi nami. אם כן
מאי ולא כלום? im ken mai velo klum? Then it wouldn't just
say you can't break it, it wouldn't say you can't break even
the smallest amount, there can be absolutely zero interruption. So we're not
just saying you can't have them in different hours, we're saying it
literally has to be one sound. So רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that
considers it one unit, would say no breath, it's literally one sound
that starts תקיעה, tekiah goes to תרועה, teruah, ends with תקיעה. tekiah
The רבנן Rabbanan say it's three sounds, but one group. And because
it's one group, there can be like a breath between them, but
they have to be somehow coherent, a little bit. It's not exactly
clear what the limit of that would be. And then the final
opinion says they're completely independent and you can have nine different sounds
at nine different hours during the day. And the רבנן Rabbanan clearly
disagree with that. And that's why there are three opinions: completely nine
independent, and this is for ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, but the same,
I'm sorry, because we're moving back and forth, but the same issue
would apply in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. All right, if you
want to do it with a group of three, is it one
sound? Is it three sounds but a group, so they have to
be close by, but you take breaths between them, maybe you even
have to take a breath between them because you have to make
them separate sounds? Or but it's at least a group, or a
more extreme position, which is it's not even a group, they're completely
independent sounds.
You had a question about something, understanding who’s obligated here. It's just
not possible. Right.
This is not talking about a person. No, no, no, no. So
that's a very good point. We are not talking here about a
personal
obligation. No, that's borrowing from language of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana. We're
comparing, when we mention the nine blasts, we are making an analogy
to, we're assuming the same issue about the trumpet blasts by the
קרבנות korbanot and how you conceptualize תקיעה tekiah, תרועה teruah, תקיעה tekiah.
is exactly the same issues that arise by blowing the שופר shofar
on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana. No, but I'm just saying the word
יצא yatza is used in a ראש השנה Rosh Hashana discussion where
we're talking about my, not the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, my individual
obligation. When we're talking about the trumpet blasts, it's not about individuals
satisfying their obligation. It's about
how the כהנים Kohanim as a collective have to bring the קרבנות.
korbanot. So it's just talking about the rituals associated with the קרבן.
korban.
But it says חצי מצוה, chatzi mitzvah, that was also.
Yeah, so that is a good point. Yeah, the phrase, you're right,
חצי מצוה chatzi mitzvah was a funny phrase because it's not like
we think about doing a מצוה mitzvah and being יוצא. yotzei. So
that's why I reframed it as
half a sound, half a ritual act. But you're right. Talking about
normally when you talk about certain things which are part of the
עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you don't think about
them the same way when you talk about personal מצוות mitzvot and
being יוצא yotzei in the same way. That's absolutely correct.
Correct. This was sort of like the, on the כהנים. Kohanim. No,
I would say on the כהנים Kohanim as a collective, how are
we bring, how to bring the קרבנות. korbanot. That's really what the
obligation is: how the כהנים Kohanim bring the קרבנות, korbanot, not any
particular person, any particular כהן's Kohen obligation. Okay, but very good point.
Yeah, there are some מצוות mitzvot that really do are not personal
obligation. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says, now we get to the
issue that's very relevant for us: שנים עשר יום בשנה מחלל בחליל,
shneim asar yom bashana mechalel bachailil, twelve days in a year that
you would have the flute play alone, or only on those days
would the flute play according to רש״י. Rashi. מאי שנא הני? mai
shna hanei? Now, of course, we're not talking what's special about the
חליל, chalil, presumably, we had to pick something to make it, to
distinguish it. But fine, so whatever, we picked the flute. But what's
special about these days? הואיל ויחיד גומר בהן את ההלל, hoil veyachid
gomer bahen et haHallel, because the individual, I'll talk about each of
these words here, finishes the הלל, Hallel, says the full
הלל. Hallel. דאמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק, d'amar Rabbi
Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak, here's רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. says
in the name of רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק. Rabbi Shimon ben Yozadak.
I'm going to read a little then I'll go back and discuss
it. שמונה עשר יום שהיחיד גומר בהן את ההלל. Shmonah asar yom
shehayachid gomer bahen et haHallel. There are eighteen, now we just said
twelve, now we're saying eighteen, but you'll see how it works out.
Eighteen days that an individual completes the הלל, Hallel, שמונה ימי החג,
shmonah yemei hachag, eight days of סוכות, Sukkot, which is mentioned in
our משנה. Mishna. שמונה ימי חנוכה, shmonah yemei Chanukah, eight days of
חנוכה. Chanukah. Now that's easy why it's not mentioned in our משנה.
Mishna. Why is it not mentioned in our משנה? Mishna? Would it
be in the משנה? Mishna? No. No, the משנה Mishna was written
after חנוכה. Chanukah.
Is it an earlier one?
No, come on, but for a better reason. Go ahead.
חנוכה Chanukah those dates when... No, I think you're thinking way too
hard.
The משנה Mishna is about when you play special instruments associated with
קרבנות. korbanot. There's no special חנוכה Chanukah קרבן. korban. Okay, so you
can have some days that you say הלל Hallel that don't translate
into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash because there's no קרבן korban associated
with them. So that's the eight days of הלל Hallel not mentioned
in our משנה, Mishna, okay, but we have eight days of
סוכות, Sukkot, ויום טוב הראשון של פסח, veyom tov harishon shel Pesach,
first day of פסח, Pesach, ויום טוב של עצרת, veyom tov shel
atzeret, or whatever, and שבועות, Shavuot, that's ten. Now, also though, it
does not mention, this is another reason why it's not exactly the
same as the משנה, Mishna, that's ten, our משנה Mishna had twelve,
what other two days did our משנה Mishna have? ערב פסח. Erev
Pesach.
ערב פסח, Erev Pesach,
the bringing of the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, ראשון ושני. rishon vesheni.
So that is only a הלל Hallel significance in the context of
a קרבן, korban, meaning in the context of bringing a קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, there's no קדושת היום kedushat hayom there that it has
significance when you don't have a בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. There the
praising and the הלל Hallel is associated with bringing the... so they
would say הלל Hallel by when they would bring it. But for
us nowadays we're not going to say הלל Hallel on those days.
Okay, so it's not exactly the same list. There are days that
we say הלל Hallel that is not... don't have the flute because
there's no קרבנות. korbanot. There are days like חנוכה, Chanukah, there are
days that we had the flute and had הלל Hallel that we
nowadays don't have הלל, Hallel, which is the days of the bringing
of the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, because they don't have the significance
for us today when there's no קרבן. korban. But basically once you
account for the differences, the basic core are the days you play
the flute are the days you say הלל, Hallel, and that's actually
true about the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach as well, except we don't
retain that. So the days of the flute are the days of
הלל, Hallel, and now we're going to analyze that.
Yes, I've got the eight days סוכות, Sukkot, eight days חנוכה, Chanukah,
and what were the other two in the גמרא? Gemara?
שבועות Shavuot and פסח, Pesach, first day of פסח. Pesach. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says that gives you eighteen. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, I mean so so this ends, by the way,
ובגולה, uvagolah, and outside of Israel, עשרים ואחד, esrin ve-echad, they are
twenty-one days of הלל, Hallel, because you add second day יום טוב.
yom tov. תשעה ימי החג, tesha yemei hachag, nine days of סוכות,
Sukkot, ושמונה ימי חנוכה, ushmonah yemei Chanukah, ושני ימים טובים של פסח,
ushnei yamim tovim shel Pesach, extra day for פסח, Pesach, ושני ימים
טובים של עצרת, ushnei yamim tovim shel atzeret, next day for שבועות,
Shavuot, so three extra days for the three רגלים regalim gets you
from eighteen to twenty-one.
Giving a second day for שבועות Shavuot is an old... second day
in the גולה golah too?
Yeah, definitely. Okay, מאי שנא דחג? mai shna dechag? Now, now we
get to the obvious question. Right, there's two a couple of obvious
questions you should ask here, which is number one, the most obvious
is why on סוכות Sukkot every day, and on פסח Pesach only
once? And the other question is why on the רגלים regalim and
not on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, although
you could probably intuit an answer for that one. But first the
more obvious question, which is why every day for סוכות Sukkot and
only the first day for פסח? Pesach? Now before we get the
answer, what's the answer that most people know to that?
Why don't you say a full הלל? Hallel? Because of the Egyptians
drowning.
Yes, exactly. So the classic answer based on the מדרש, Midrash, which
is not in the גמרא Gemara and never given and not given
in an הלכה halakhic discourse, is that the מדרש Midrash says that
on the last day of פסח, Pesach, on the יום שביעי של
פסח, yom shevii shel Pesach, right, the מלאכי- malakhi you know, the
מלאכים malakhim when the Egyptians were drowning on the ים סוף Yam
Suf the מלאכים malakhim wanted to sing שירה, shira, and God says
מעשה ידי טובעים בים ואתם אומרים שירה? ma'aseh yadai tove'im bayam ve'atem
omrim shira? Now actually it's interesting because of course who did sing
שירה? shira? בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So to say that's the reason
we don't say הלל, Hallel, you know the message there is is
that A to acknowledge the tragedy, but to say for the people
that were actually directly being saved, they also had to acknowledge their
salvation. But for the angels who weren't being saved, they had they
could not ignore the human tragedy. Okay, so to say that's the
reason we don't say הלל Hallel is interesting. Then you would have
to say okay we're maybe more like the angels and not בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael because we are not directly experiencing the salvation, we're
removed from it. But anyway, you're supposed to see yourself... I understand,
but that's on the first day. Anyway, so first of all it's
interesting the use of that מדרש Midrash to say why we don't
say it the seventh day. Then the argument goes, if you're not
saying it for the seventh day, you can't be saying it for
חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, which is less significant than the seventh day.
That's normally what everybody is taught in grade school. Okay, that's not
what the גמרא Gemara says. Now we're going to find out what
the גמרא's Gemara real answer... Okay, the real answer but a tech-
more הלכה halakhic answer. Let's take a look at what the גמרא
Gemara says. Okay, מאי שנא דחג דאמרינן כל יומא ויומא? mai shna
dechag d'amrinan kol yoma veyoma? Why do we say it every day
of סוכות? Sukkot? ומאי שנא דפסח דלא אמרינן? umai shna dePesach delo
amrinan? Why don't we say it every day of פסח? Pesach? It
says, כל יומא דחג חלוקין בקרבנותיהם. kol yoma dechag chalukin bekurbanoteihem. On
סוכות Sukkot every day has a different קרבנות. korbanot. Right? Because every
day's קרבנות korbanos, *korbanot* is, you know, it goes, it goes down,
13, 12, 11, etc. The פסח Pesach *Pesach* אין חלוקין בקרבנותיהן *ein
halukin be-korbenoteihen*, on פסח Pesach. *Pesach* all the קרבנות korbanos. *korbanot* are
the same each day. Now, why does that matter? Well, it could
mean—we understand that it could matter in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
*Beit Hamikdash* that somehow it's sort of seen as like a continuation
of the first day if we're doing this by—with the קרבנות korbanos.
*korbanot*, there's nothing distinct, so been there done that, as opposed to
on the other days of סוכות Succos, *Sukkot* there's something distinct. But
the question is we also translate this for us today in terms
of our saying of הלל Hallel *Hallel*. So that sort of puts
you in one of two positions. Either you have to say that
our saying of הלל Hallel, *Hallel* really is related—is only somehow a
זכר *zecher* or or connected to the saying of הלל Hallel? *Hallel*
they would do on the קרבנות korbanos *korbanot*. We normally don't want
to say that, right? We normally want to think that the day
itself, we're responding to the praising of God of the day itself
and the significance of the day itself, not just like we're connecting
to how they would do it when they would bring a קרבן
*korban*. So if that's true, how do we explain the difference—now you
know why they quote the מדרש Midrash *Midrash*—because how do we explain
why the difference of קרבנות *korbanot* means we don't say הלל Hallel
*Hallel*? Like there's no direct explanation. So the best explanation given is
to say that the קרבנות *korbanot* are not the reason, but they
are a סימן *siman* about the—about the difference of the חגים *chagim*.
That basically they signal the fact that on פסח Pesach. *Pesach* we
look at the whole יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* as basically
one unit, and on סוכות Succos *Sukkot* we look at every day
as a separate קדושה kedusha *kedusha*, a separate unit. And therefore the
fact that you bring קרבנות *korbanot* is an indication of the fact
that each day is distinct. So therefore if you said הלל Hallel
*Hallel* for the entire unit of פסח Pesach? *Pesach*, you said הלל
Hallel. *Hallel* for פסח *Pesach*. But if you said הלל Hallel *Hallel*
for סוכות Succos *Sukkot*, you only said it for one day of
סוכות Sukkot, *Sukkot*, each day is a separate unit. Now what's fine,
even if you say that, the next question is why? What's the
logic for that? So, you know, I would think that the best
answer for that is—and you can come up with your own answers—but
I would suggest that the best answer for that is is that
פסח *Pesach* was actually a process, right? The the Exodus, the גאולה
*geulah*, right, was it started with יציאת מצרים Yetzias Mitzrayim, *Yetziat Mitzrayim*,
and it culminated in קריעת ים סוף *Kriat Yam Suf*. That was
all one process, so one process, it's a narrative, right? It's all
connected. So whereas the—what do we commemorate on on סוכות *Sukkot*? כי
בסכות הושבתי את בני ישראל Yisrael, *Ki basukkot hoshavti et bnei Yisrael*,
you know, as everybody says, you could have sat in סוכות *Sukkot*
on any single day of the year. There's nothing particular one day
over the other day. So therefore in a way, it—because in a
way it—you know, maybe it's a little ironic, but I would say
that—I knew you would say that—but anyway I would still say since
there's no particular narrative, there's nothing that connects one day to the
next. So it's not so—if you want to commemorate it for eight
days, each day is a separate commemoration. There's no somehow way in
which day two is connected to day one. As opposed to פסח
*Pesach*, every day is connected to every previous day, it's all part
of the process of going out of מצרים *Mitzrayim* leading to קריעת
ים סוף *Kriat Yam Suf*. That is the best that I can
do. But what about the first—the first—קריעת ים סוף *Kriat Yam Suf*
and the special seven days of פסח *Pesach*—so right, we have to
do—we do the math and we explain it that way. I know,
so if it's so explicitly connected to the קרבנות *korbanot*, then why
is ערב פסח *Erev Pesach* different?
Why is ערב *Erev*—well, the קרבן *korban* of ערב פסח *Erev Pesach*
was distinct
from the קרבן מוסף *korban musaf*. It was a קרבן יחיד yachid.
*korban yachid*, it was a different קרבן *korban* and so on. Clearly
there was a very—you know, a
huge distinction there between the קרבנות *korbanot*.
Anyway, that's the
best that I can do. It's either trying to explain it somehow
as indicating that or as—what did I say?—or or somehow saying that
our הלל Hallel *Hallel* just is linked to the הלל Hallel *Hallel*
of the קרבנות *korbanot*, which is—which is something (a) we wouldn't want
to say and (b) it's not going to work anyway because we're
going to wind up saying—we say הלל Hallel. *Hallel* on חנוכה Chanukah?
*Chanukah* which doesn't have to do with the קרבנות *korbanot*. So somehow
you have to explain—I think that the קרבנות *korbanot* are a סימן
*siman* to some bigger distinction, some bigger division. There actually is an
important—there—it's one way you see this distinction playing itself out and to
prove that it's not just about the קרבנות *korbanot* is about the
ברכה bracha *beracha* of שהחיינו *shehecheyanu*. We make a שהחיינו *shehecheyanu* on
on קידוש *kiddush* on the last day of סוכות *Sukkot*, on שמיני
עצרת *Shemini Atzeret*, but we do not make it on the last
day of פסח *Pesach*. Why? Exactly for this reason that that—or you
could say there's another reason as well that שמיני עצרת *Shemini Atzeret*
is רגל בפני עצמו *regel bifnei atzmo*, right? You could say it's
not exactly associated with that, it's because it is in other ways
in which שמיני עצרת *Shemini Atzeret* is distinct from the prior days.
But anyway, but at least it's partly also because of—I'll give you
another example here, here's a better example which you won't count—blame on
שמיני עצרת *Shemini Atzeret*. שבת Shabbos! *Shabbat* during חול המועד פסח Chol
HaMoed Pesach? *Chol Hamoed Pesach*, when you read the הפטרה *Haftarah*, here,
Dov will know the answer to this, Dov, what do you say—what's
the difference between the ברכת הפטרה *birkhat haftarah* on שבת Shabbos חול
המועד פסח Chol HaMoed Pesach, *Shabbat Chol Hamoed Pesach* and שבת Shabbos
חול המועד סוכות Chol HaMoed Succos. *Shabbat Chol Hamoed Sukkot*? Do you
know? We say regular? On שבת Shabbos חול המועד סוכות *Shabbat Chol
Hamoed Sukkot*, you mention ועל יום yom הסוכות הזה *ve-al yom ha-Sukkot
hazeh*, whatever. And what—what—what do you say on the רגל *regel*? ועל
יום חג הסוכות הזה *ve-al yom chag ha-Sukkot hazeh*, and on שבת
Shabbos חול המועד פסח Chol HaMoed Pesach. *Shabbat Chol Hamoed Pesach*, you
only say ועל יום השבת הזה *ve-al yom ha-Shabbat hazeh*, you don't
say יום חג הפסח הזה *yom chag ha-Pesach hazeh*. Why? It's חול
המועד שבת Shabbos *Chol Hamoed Shabbat*. Because פסח *Pesach* is seen as
one big unit. unit, the day itself does not have some distinctive
identity and therefore, as opposed to on פסח, סוכות, each day is
seen as having some distinctive identity, so if you're making a ברכה
אחרונה, bracha achrona, you acknowledge the identity of the day as חול
המועד סוכות. So there are a number of הלכות halachos where it's
clear that this is not just about the קרבנות, that really there
is a difference between conceptually whether פסח is a unit of seven
and סוכות are seven distinct days. Okay, so that's why you say
הלל Hallel, differently. What? Well, you also take, let's say, there's a
משנה mishna on the first day of סוכות that does not exist
on other days. The ארבע מינים. arba minim. Right, same is true
about פסח. No, in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash you did it
all seven days anyway. You still have מצה. matzah. Yes, but סיפור
יציאת מצרים, Sippur Yetzias Mitzrayim, the חיוב chiyuv of מצה, matzah, so
you're saying the theme doesn't carry through as much as what you're
saying. The theme of לולב lulav מדאורייתא m'de'oraisa doesn't carry through as
much as it does on, which is a very good point. Okay,
that's a good point. I know, but the תורה Torah still says
שבעת ימים shivas yamim and there's still a חיוב, chiyuv, there's still
an idea, you still do it. Okay. Alright, okay, well you also
take לולב וערבה, lulav v'arava, but that's because of the רבנן. rabbanan.
Okay, so that's that. Now, let me say another point that's not
discussed in the גמרא. Gemara. The phrase גומר gomair and the phrase
יחיד. yachid Okay? So, what would they do on the other days,
on חול המועד פסח? What would they do on ראש חודש? Rosh
Chodesh? We'll talk in a minute why you don't say ראש חודש.
Rosh Chodesh. So תוספות Tosafot is uncertain. There's גמרות Gemaros that say
that there was a מנהג minhag to do like a type of
a חצי הלל, chatzi Hallel, jump around, skip around. You're saying outside
the בית המקדש you're saying? No, nowadays. But this is saying גומר
את ההלל gomair es ha'Hallel is talking about nowadays for us. Okay,
so does גומר gomair indicate that on other relevant days, ראש חודש,
Rosh Chodesh, חול המועד פסח, you would say it, but you would
not say it whole, you would do some other חצי הלל? chatzi
Hallel? Or תוספות Tosafot says it's not so clear to him. He
thinks that maybe you wouldn't say it at all and the מנהג
minhag to say it developed later than this statement. Okay, so that's
one question, but clearly there are גמרות Gemaros that say that on
the other days they would do a half הלל, Hallel. the question
is, is that already indicated by this statement. Now another question related
to that is, would you make a ברכה bracha on the half
הלל? Hallel It's a major debate if you make a ברכה bracha
on the half הלל Hallel. on the other days, especially if that
was a later מנהג minhag and it wasn't even indicated at all
that the רבנים rabbonim were telling you to do it. And that
gets to the question under do you make ברכות berachos on מנהגים
minhagim and so on. Now obviously the אשכנזים Ashkenazim do, but the
ספרדים, Sefardim, what do the ספרדים Sefardim say? When they do a
full הלל Hallel they say לגמור את ההלל, ligmor es ha'Hallel, which
is גומר את ההלל, gomair es ha'Hallel, and when they say a
חצי הלל chatzi Hallel no ברכה bracha at all. And they only
say it בציבור. b'tzibbur. Do you say חצי הלל chatzi Hallel ביחידות,
b'yechidus, ספרדים? Sefardim? No no no, only בציבור. b'tzibbur. Okay, because that's
the next question. Next question is, besides the ברכה bracha and the
fact we do actually say a חצי הלל, chatzi Hallel, that's clear
from the גמרות, Gemaros, what does יחיד yachid, mean, גומר את ההלל?
gomair es ha'Hallel? Right, that suggests that on other days, if you're
a יחיד, yachid maybe there's a difference between יחיד and ציבור. tzibbur.
So there leads to some to say that even if you say
חצי הלל chatzi Hallel with a ברכה bracha. during the other days,
that's only if you're saying it בציבור. b'tzibbur. But if you're saying
it ביחידות, b'yechidus, maybe you don't say it at all, or maybe
you certainly shouldn't say a ברכה. bracha. And there are definitely those
opinions out there. We פוסקין pasken that even if you say it
ביחידות b'yechidus you say it with a ברכה. Why? Because it's one
of the possibilities, רבינו תם'ס שיטה, Rabbeinu Tam's shitta, we פוסקין pasken
that way. But okay, but we sometimes have a ספק, safek, we
don't leave everything as a ספק. safek. Anyway, so that's in terms
of the phrase יחיד גומר את ההלל. yachid gomair es ha'Hallel. Let's
keep on reading the גמרא Gemara now. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
wants to analyze why we don't say it, we know now why
you don't say it on the separate days of פסח. Now it's
going to analyze why you don't say it on some other days.
Like why don't you say it on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh etc. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. So
now you're saying the whole difference is distinct קרבנות. So the גמרא
Gemara says שבת דחלוקה בקרבנותיה לימרא? Shabbos d'chaluka b'korbanoseha leimra? Say it
on שבת! Shabbos Every שבת Shabbos has distinct קרבנות. It says לא
איקרי מועד. Lo ikri moed. No no no. First you have to
be considered a מועד moed like a יום טוב Yom Tov? to
say הלל. Hallel Presumably, although the גמרא Gemara never actually says this,
here's an interesting question. Are we saying הלל Hallel to respond to
the historical events that are being commemorated? Or are we saying הלל
Hallel. to just respond to the קדושת היום? kedushas hayom? Okay, now
what would that make sense? Why would we say הלל Hallel if
it was the קדושת היום, kedushas hayom, isn't the קדושה kedusha of
שבת Shabbos higher than the קדושה kedusha of יום טוב? Yom Tov,
How would you explain it if it's not linked to the historical
events? So הרב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik has a beautiful point where he
says like this. He says while you're allowed to do מלאכה, melacha,
cooking etc. on יום טוב, Yom Tov he says there's the following
distinction holds. He says שבת Shabbos. conceptually is we welcome the קדושה
kedusha of שבת Shabbos or God, the קדושה kedusha into our zone,
into our space. It occurs every week, it's our week, we do
a קבלת שבת, Kabbalas Shabbos, God comes into our space. The קדושה
kedusha of יום טוב Yom Tov he says, if the model is
the רגלים regalim and עלייה לרגל, aliyah l'regel, so therefore he says
what the קדושה kedusha of יום טוב Yom Tov is is more
we're entering God's space. Why he said that there's not a... there's
a קבלת שבת, Kabbalat Shabbat, there's not a קבלת יום טוב. Kabbalat
Yom Tov. He has a lot of explanations about this. Anyway, certainly
by יום טוב Yom Tov. there's a greater sense of although the
קדושה kedusha, is not the same, normal ways of measuring קדושה, kedusha
שבת Shabbos is higher, but somewhat of a greater sense of directly
in the presence of God by יום טוב. Yom Tov, And it's
more unusual, it's a rarer. So I think that could connect to
what this גמרא Gemara is saying as well about the מועד. Moed.
Meaning our answer to why you wouldn't say it on שבת Shabbos
is there's no particular שמחה simcha to respond to, it's linked to
a concept of שמחה. simcha. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that,
it says somehow the מועדים Moadim which is not really fully explained
and seems to be focusing somehow on the קדושה kedusha. or the
identity of the day. Let's keep on reading. Wait, did you say
שבת Shabbos is not called a מועד? Moed? Right. Now, of course,
I know, that's always the point, that the גמרא Gemara when it
wants to, right, says that שבת Shabbos, is in the list of
מועדים Moadim because in the beginning of אלה מועדי השם, Eileh Moadei
Hashem, it lists שבת. Shabbos Right, yes. But even more directly, וביום
שמחתכם ובמועדיכם, u'veyom simchatchem u'vemoadeichem, right? And there's a מחלוקת machloket as
to what the מועדים Moadim mean, and then don't some and then
because they do it every day,
so that either means every day is a מועד Moed or it
would be שבת Shabbos? and then directly about the חצוצרות chatzoztrot though,
no? Yeah, that's a good point, how they have that פסוק pasuk
is read. Look, when we want to, we say שבת Shabbos is
included in the מועדים, Moadim, and when we don't want to, we
say it's not included. Okay, so we could say שבת Shabbat, commemorates
מעשה בראשית, Ma'aseh Bereishit, you could say שבת commemorates יציאת מצרים, commemorates
a historical event with a miracle or whatever. Right, which is... oh,
so right. So yeah, so obviously it's not. Right. So I... which
and the גמרא Gemara doesn't... right, so maybe that's why the גמרא
Gemara doesn't make that distinction. But the גמרא's Gemara distinction does not
seem to be the one we would naturally go to, which is
about a very special day and a very special... maybe that's what
מועד Moed means. Like it's too regular then, it doesn't have that
specialness to be saying הלל. Hallel. It's not exactly clear why that
should be the difference. Let's read a little bit more. ראש חודש
דאיקרי מועד לימא, Rosh Chodesh d'ikrei moed leima, how about ראש חודש,
Rosh Chodesh, that's called a מועד. Moed. And again, I think that
really proves that the גמרא's Gemara not thinking about miracles and historical,
commemorating historical events. It's just focusing very technically on מועד. Moed. So
the גמרא Gemara says לא איקדש בעשיית מלאכה. lo ikadesh b'asiyat melacha.
No, there's no prohibition of doing מלאכה, melacha, so it's not distinct
enough. And how do you know it's associated with not doing מלאכה?
melacha? דכתיב השיר יהיה לכם כליל התקדש חג. dechativ hashir yihiyeh lachem
keleil hitkadesh chag. The song, meaning the הלל, Hallel? will be for
you like the night sanctified for the holiday. לילה המקודש לחג, laila
hamikudash l'chag, it's sanctified meaning that there's no מלאכה, melacha, טעון שירה,
taun shirah, you do הלל. Hallel? שאינו מקודש לחג אין טעון שירה,
she'eino mekudash l'chag ein taun shirah, not when it's not. So basically
we're going to ask, okay, so now we have a very technical
explanation. We have yet to mention miracle, history, anything, and which explains
also why to read the קרבנות as indicating the question of קדושה.
kedusha So it's a particular type of a קדושת היום. kedushat hayom.
A קדושת היום kedushat hayom that is number one, איסור מלאכה, issur
melacha, number two, a קדושת היום kedushat hayom that is somehow מועד,
Moed, it's not so regular like שבת, it's somehow a special day,
a מועד. Moed. But it's about a קדושה and a distinct קדושת
היום kedushat hayom as opposed to חול המועד פסח. So somehow linking
to קדושת היום kedushat hayom very different than what we would have
said הלל Hallel is about. Yes, though. What's this מועד ראש חודש
Moed Rosh Chodesh being called a מועד? Moed? Yeah, so why is
ראש חודש... Rosh Chodesh... so רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק pasuk קרא
עלי מועד kara alay moed that the גמרא Gemara does דרשה drasha
by, then talking about ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Ah, right, it's אלה
מועדי... Eileh moadei... no wait, in פנחס, Pinchas, wait, in פנחס Pinchas
is it mentioned in the מועדים? Moadim? In the whole פנחס, Pinchas,
and שבת is mentioned there too. What? It's not called a מועד
Moed in there. Doesn't it... isn't it in the opening, when it
starts there with שבת? You'll look it up. Anyway, I think that's
why רש"י Rashi quoted the other דרשה. drasha. So good, there could
have been another answer and the גמרא Gemara could have gone either
way. It could have that שבת is a מועד, Moed, that would
have gotten stuck that way. ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh isn't. All right,
let's keep on going. Now, basically though, a little, I think, disappointing
maybe to what we would have thought, or challenging to what we
would have thought. Not linked to history, not linked to miracle, linked
to some aspect of the קדושת היום, kedushat hayom, which is why
I think drawing on the idea that הרב סולובייצ'יק Harav Soloveitchik said
about the sense of a certain קדושת יום טוב kedushat Yom Tov
putting us in the presence of God is probably the best way
to explain what's going on here. Let's keep on going. The גמרא
Gemara says like this: ראש השנה ויום הכיפורים דאיקרי מועד. Rosh Hashanah
v'Yom HaKippurim d'ikrei moed. Rosh Hashanah and Yom Kippur, those are called
מועד. Moed. דאיתקדש בעשיית מלאכה לימא, D'itkadesh b'asiyat melacha leima, how about
say it on Rosh Hashanah and Yom Kippur? Those are called מועד,
Moed, you can't do מלאכה melacha on those days. Okay. Now we
might have said, oh, those maybe aren't days of שמחה. simcha. Okay,
now we'll see what the גמרא Gemara answers, whether it's exactly that
answer or not. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says משום דרבי אבהו,
mishum d'Rabbi Abbahu, because of a statement of Rabbi Abbahu. דאמר רבי
אבהו אמרו מלאכי השרת לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, D'amar Rabbi Abbahu amru
malachei hasharet lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu, here's where we quote the angels.
Not by שביעי של פסח, Shevii shel Pesach, here. The angels said
to God: ריבונו של עולם, Ribbono shel Olam, master of the universe,
מפני מה אין ישראל אומרים שירה לפניך בראש השנה וביום הכיפורים? mipnei
mah ein Yisrael omrim shirah lefanecha b'Rosh Hashanah u'v'Yom HaKippurim? Why are
the Jews not saying שירה shirah today, on Rosh Hashanah and Yom
Kippur? אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said to them: אפשר מלך יושב
על כיסא הדין? Efshar melech yoshev al kissei hadin? Is it possible
the king is sitting on the seat of judgment, וספרי חיים וספרי
מתים פתוחים לפניו, v'sifrei chayim v'sifrei meisim ptuchim lefanav, and the books
of life and death are open in front of him, וישראל אומרים
שירה? v'Yisrael omrim shirah? And Israel should say song? אמר להם, Amar
lahem, He said to them, אפשר מלך יושב על כסא הדין, Efshar
melech yoshev al kiseh hadin, is it possible the King is sitting
on the seat of judgment, וספר חיים וספר מתים פתוחים לפניו, v'sefer
chayim v'sefer meisim ptuchim lifanav, and the books of life and death
are open before Him, וישראל אומרים שירה לפני, v'Yisrael omrim shira lifanai,
and they're singing song? So they should be trembling, they should be
fearful, and therefore it's not a time to say הלל. Hallel Now,
what does this mean? You could say it simply means that הלל
Hallel, is associated with, and this maybe is what we would have
said before this whole thing about מועד Moed and עשיית מלאכה, Asiyat
Melacha, why not just say it's linked to the מצוה mitzvah of
שמחה? simcha? There's a מצוה mitzvah of שמחת הרגל, simchas haregel, ושמחת
בחגך, v'samachta b'chagecha, right? And that would have been הלל Hallel associated
with שמחה. simcha. Now maybe you could say that is what the
גמרא Gemara says. That at the end of the day, that's what
the גמרא Gemara says. Why not ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, why these days? In the end of the day,
it boils down to whether there's a שמחת הרגל simchas haregel or
not, a שמחת יום טוב, simchas yom tov, and it's not on
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. That's possible, though
the גמרא Gemara did not say שמחה simcha before. And actually, this
מדרש Midrash leads to an interesting מחלוקת machlokes in the ראשונים Rishonim
and in the פוסקים, Poskim, whether there's a מצוה mitzvah of שמחה
simcha on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. And one of the questions is,
if somebody is so afraid of the יום הדין, Yom Hadin, can
they fast on ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah? Is it מותר muttar to
fast on ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah? And some say it's מותר, muttar,
and others say it's אסור. assur. There's a מצוה mitzvah of שמחה
simcha on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you can't be מבטל mevatel the
מצוה mitzvah of שמחה simcha on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. They tell
a famous story about the בית הלוי, Beis Halevi, רב חיים בריסקר'ס
Rav Chaim Brisker's father, where he was saying, you know, "People say
rabbis are so מחמיר, machmir, I don't know what they're talking about,
I'm a big מקיל! meikel! Those who say it's אסור assur to
fast on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, I say it's מותר!" muttar! You
know, he had a list of like three or four things like
that. Anyway, okay, so there's an interesting הלכה halacha question whether, by
the way, there's a huge difference between the way ספרדים Sefardim and
אשכנזים Ashkenazim celebrate ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. As אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, it's all
about אימת הדין eimas hadin and יראה yira and all about, you
know, היכא שירה. heicha shira. For ספרדים, Sefardim, I think they, you
know, it's much more the aspect of שמחה simcha associated with ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So it's interesting, number one, is הלל Hallel. linked
to שמחה simcha or not? It's not necessarily, it could be what
the גמרא Gemara is saying, maybe it's not. Maybe it's saying maybe
there is an aspect of שמחה simcha on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
that still doesn't mean you take it to the point of saying
הלל. Hallel Okay, הלל Hallel is taking it about like going too
far, you know, there needs to be a certain element of אימת
הדין. eimas hadin. Right. Okay, now, that being said, there's another beautiful
מדרש that has to be weighed against this, which says that, you
know, that God says to the angels, I think, I don't remember
if it starts with the angels' question or whatever, but anyway, God
says to the angels, he says, "Normally if somebody has a דין,
din, he comes, you know, he comes to the judge dressed in
שחורים, shchorim, מעוטף שחורים, mutaf shchorim, he like dresses in a way
that shows how miserable he is and so on, and how humble
he is." He says, "But my children, they come, they're לובשי לבנים,
lovshei levanim, they dress nicely for יום טוב, Yom Tov, they show
that they have a confidence that they will be, that they will
be found meritorious בדין." badin. So it's like a very, like, interesting
balance. It doesn't, you know, there's a sense of having a certain
amount of joy and confidence and so on related to the יום
and your relationship with God, but not going overboard, not taking it
too far, so you don't say הלל. Hallel, Right. Okay, so that's
in terms of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
תוספות Tosafos by the way says that it just says, why do
the Jews not say הלל? Hallel. It doesn't say why do we
not say הלל? Hallel. Which seems like the angels do say הלל
Hallel. on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. And
therefore he says that, you know, that if you take a look
at this אומרו, omro, that תוספות אומרו, Tosafos omro, the last line,
he says וכך אמרו ובראש השנה וביום הכיפורים אין לדלג והחיות ישוררו
וכרובים יפארו. v'kach omru uv'Rosh Hashanah uv'Yom Hakippurim ein ledaleg v'hachayos yishoreru
u'chruvim yefaeru. Now, for anybody, I don't know, for you, but I
never say that during the other 363 days of the year or
whatever, right? Only on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור Yom
Kippur do we have that נוסח. nusach. But anyway, some people said
you should not say on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור
Yom Kippur "the angels will burst out in song" because maybe the
angels don't sing. And תוספות Tosafos says, no, no, no, we don't
sing, but the angels still sing. Okay. And anyway, if you've been
to the HIR for ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, there's plenty of singing
that we do too. All right, moving on. Now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: לחנוכה דלא הכי ולא הכי וקאמר, la'Chanukah d'lo hachi
v'lo hachi v'ka'amar, how about חנוכה? Chanukah? It's not got any of
these, it's not a יום טוב, Yom Tov it's nothing! So why
do we do it on חנוכה? Chanukah, אה משום ניסא! ah, mishum
nisa! Oh, guess what? That's cause of the miracle. Okay, which seems
like the other things are not directly linked to the miracle, which
by the way, how about the whole idea of שבועות? Shavuos? Right,
now of course חז"ל Chazal associate שבועות Shavuos with מתן תורה, Matan
Torah, but it's not associated that way in the תורה.
Torah. So it really
seems that the הלל Hallel, of יום טוב is not according to
the גמרא Gemara associated with the miracle, which explains why it gave
all those other answers and so on, it's related to the קדושת
היום. kedushas hayom. But חנוכה, Chanukah you don't need קדושת היום, kedushas
hayom, חנוכה Chanukah is about the miracle, and particularly let's not forget
that חנוכה Chanukah has the special aspect of פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa.
So to say that by חנוכה Chanukah. the miracle translates in a
proclamation in הלל, Hallel right, it works both ways. Number one, you
can't associate with קדושת היום, kedushas hayom, and number two, there in
particular the נס nes should demand הלל Hallel. because of the aspect
of פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa. So that's why you do it on
חנוכה. Chanukah So now the obvious next question is, פורים דאיכא ניסא
לימא, Purim d'ika nisa leima, how about פורים? Purim? There's also פרסומי
הנס pirsumei hanes and there's a miracle, so let's say it on
פורים. Purim. So אמר רבי יצחק לפי שאינו אומר שירה על נס
שבחוץ לארץ. Amar Rabi Yitzchak lefi she'eino omrim shira al nes sheb'chutz
la'aretz. Oh, that happened outside ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So you don't.
That's not—that doesn't have eternal significance. No, we're going to get to
that. So the גמרא Gemara asks it by רב נחמן בר יצחק,
Rav Nachman bar Yitzhak, הרי יציאת מצרים דנס שבחוץ לארץ הוא Harei
Yetziat Mitzrayim de-Nes she-be-chutz la-Aretz hu too? How about פסח? That was
a נס שבחוץ לארץ Nes she-be-chutz la-Aretz too? And you could say
סוכות, right? That was also חוץ לארץ. chutz la-Aretz. ואמרינן הלל, Ve-amrinan
Hallel, we say הלל. Hallel Now the best answer here should have
been what? That has nothing to do with a miracle. We just
spent the first top of the page telling you why you say
הלל Hallel. there and the word miracle didn't come out of our
mouths once, right? And that really should be the answer, that that
has nothing to do with the miracle. But the גמרא, Gemara, at
least the answer the גמרא Gemara gives, seems to now buy into
the idea that it is related to a miracle, okay, which then
then you go back to all the other questions and you can
rewrite the whole previous גמרא, Gemara, ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, שבת, right?
There's totally different answers. So anyway, it's very interesting the way the
גמרא Gemara shifts now into the miracle mode. And it says like
this, so what's the answer? So it says כדתניא, ke-detanya, עד שלא
נכנסו ישראל לארץ הוכשרו כל הארצות לומר שירה. ad she-lo nichnasu Yisrael
la-Aretz huchshru kol ha-aratzot lomar shirah. So then there ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael did not yet have its full distinction, so you could associate
שירה shirah and acknowledge the significance of הלל and so on of
miracles even in חוץ לארץ chutz la-Aretz because, but משנכנסו לארץ, mishenichnasu
la-Aretz, once they lived in the land, anything that happens in חוץ
לארץ, chutz la-Aretz, you know, it's like the New Yorker's view of
the world, right? Anything that happens out of ישראל, Yisrael it doesn't
really matter, has no real significance. So therefore, לא הוכשרו כל הארצות
לומר שירה. lo huchshru kol ha-aratzot lomar shirah. You don't say שירה
shirah on things that happen outside outside of the land. We're getting
there, we're not done. Okay, fine. Alright, anyway, so that's answer number
one. It was a נס שנעשה בחוץ לארץ, Nes she-na'asa be-chutz la-Aretz,
which brings the needing that answer, sort of the way it answered
that brings back, you know, the נס Nes into the earlier discussion,
which had been absent. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on, רב
נחמן אמר קריאתה זו היא הלילא. Rav Nachman amar kriotah zu hi
Halila. Calling, reading the מגילה Megillah is like the הלל, which basically
means that it certainly works if you emphasize פרסומי ניסא. Pirsumei Nisa.
Reading of the מגילה Megillah has an aspect of פרסומי ניסא, Pirsumei
Nisa, and so does lighting חנוכה Chanukah. candles, but here it's much
more of a verbal פרסומי ניסא, Pirsumei Nisa, of an articulate פרסומי
ניסא. Pirsumei Nisa. And therefore you do not say the הלל. Because
of this, the מאירי Meiri says that if you didn't read the
מגילה, Megillah, for some reason you didn't have the מגילה, Megillah, you'd
have to say the הלל. So he actually applies this הלכתא halachata
in a very in a very technical sense. רבא אמר, Rava amar,
רבא Rava says, בשלמא התם הללו עבדי ה׳ ולא עבדי פרעה. bishlama
hatam halelu avdei Hashem ve-lo avdei Pharoh. We sing הללו עבדי ה׳,
halelu avdei Hashem, praise the servants of God, because there's been a
real change, as we're no longer the servants of פרעה, Pharoh, right?
There was the miracle has lasting significance. הכא, hacha, here, הללו עבדי
ה׳ ולא עבדי אחשורוש? halelu avdei Hashem ve-lo avdei Achashverosh? What should
it mean? Praise, now we are servants of God, we're no longer
subject to, you know, human rulers? It's not true. In reference to
פורים, Purim, we're still subject to that those types of rulers. אכתי
עבדי אחשורוש אנן, Akti avdei Achashverosh anan, we are still subject to,
you know, to אחשורוש, Achashverosh, which by the way is not the
same for חנוכה. Chanukah חנוכה was a moment of independence, okay, of
actually being free from foreign rulers. So, so in a way what
the גמרא Gemara here is saying, you know, is saying, it's somewhat
like the חוץ לארץ chutz la-Aretz point, which oh outside of ישראל
doesn't matter, but I think it's also sort of saying that you
know it associates it's associated with a sense of like national identity.
So on one hand that means out of חוץ לארץ chutz la-Aretz
we downplay it, another way it means that if it's sort of
about gaining independence through this miracle and acknowledging that, you know, then
that's meaningful. But if yes it was a tremendous miracle but we
still are in our unredeemed state then it is not yet at
the threshold where you would say הלל. So now the גמרא Gemara
says רב נחמן דאמר קריאתה זו היא הלילא, Rav Nachman de-amar kriotah
zu hi Halila, according to רב נחמן Rav Nachman that says the
reading counts as הלל, הא תניא משנכנסו לארץ לא הוכשרו כל הארצות
לומר שירה, ha tanya mishenichnasu la-Aretz lo huchshru kol ha-aratzot lomar shirah,
how why does he need that reason? Doesn't it say once they
entered into the land you could no longer say שירה? shirah? So
he's actually saying we do say שירה. shirah. The גמרא Gemara says
the answer about אכתי עבדי אחשורוש akti avdei Achashverosh is pretty similar
to the חוץ לארץ chutz la-Aretz answer. It downplays things that happen
in the גלות Galut that are not part of our unredeemed state.
But the answer that reading the מגילה Megillah is a הלל says
we basically have an obligation to say a type of a הלל.
What about the idea you don't say הלל על נס שבחוץ לארץ?
al Nes she-be-chutz la-Aretz? So he says כיון שגלו חזרו להתירן הראשון.
keivan she-galu chazru le-heteran ha-rishon. No, if we have an independent, you
know, State of Israel, then what happens in חוץ לארץ chutz la-Aretz
has much less significance. But the נס Nes of פורים Purim happened
after during the גלות Galut period, after חורבן הבית. Churban ha-Bayit. So
in that period the נס Nes in חוץ לארץ chutz la-Aretz was
very significant and therefore it was a reason to say הלל. Okay,
let's try to read at least two a few more dots here.
We have a lot of very fascinating discussion but we got a
little behind. לא היה מכה באבוב של נחושת, Lo haya makeh be-avuv
shel nechoshet, they would not blow they would not use a copper
one. פתח בחליל וסיים באבוב, Patach be-chalil ve-siyem be-avuv, first it calls
this flute a חליל chalil then it calls it an אבוב. avuv.
אמר רב פפה, Amar Rav Papa, היינו חליל היינו אבוב, hainu chalil
hainu avuv, it's really the same thing. ואמאי קרי ליה חליל, Ve-amai
kari lei chalil, why was it called חליל? chalil? דחלי קליה de-chali
kalei because it had such a mellifluous sound. Okay, or that's what
רש״י Rashi says, a beautiful sweet sound. Like it is an Aramaic
word for that. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, let's just read a little
bit more. אבוב היה במקדש חלק. Abuv hayah ba'mikdash chalak. They had
a smooth, because it was reed or whatever, so obviously it had
a smooth- it was smooth, רש״י Rashi says it was like stripped,
you know, peeled, flute, היה דק, hayah dak, it was very thin,
חלק היה, chalak hayah, דק היה, dak hayah, it was thin, שוקנא
היה, shokana hayah, it was made out of reed, ומימות משה היה.
u'mimot Moshe hayah. It was all passed down all the way from
the time of משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. צוה המלך, Tzivah ha'melech, the
king commanded, not exactly clear which king, וציפהו זהב. ve'tzipehu zahav. He
said, oh, let's make it more beautiful. So he coated it in
gold, plated it in gold, ולא היה קולו ערב, ve'lo hayah koli
areiv, it was not a pleasant sound anymore. נטלו את ציפויו, natlu
et tzipuyo, so they stripped it of its gold, of its cover,
והיה קולו ערב, ve'hayah koli areiv, and then it was beautiful again,
כמות שהיה, ke'mot she'hayah, like it used to be. Yeah, there seems-
exactly, you can make a nice דרוש drush out of that. צלצל
היה במקדש, Tziltzal hayah ba'mikdash, they had a what do they call,
the things that- cymbals, cymbals. They had cymbals, if you look, רש״י
Rashi says צנבס tzinbas like five lines down in the narrow line,
four lines down. They had cymbals in the מקדש, mikdash, של נחושת
היה, shel nechoshet hayah, of copper it was, והיה קולו ערב, ve'hayah
koli areiv, it was a beautiful sound, ונפגם, ve'nifgam, and somehow got
damaged. ושלחו חכמים והביאו אומנין מאלכסנדריא של מצרים, ve'shalkhu chakhamim ve'heviu umanin
me'Aleksandrya shel Mitzrayim, they brought special artisans from Alexandria in Egypt, ותיקנוהו,
ve'tiknuhu, and they fixed it, ולא היה קולו ערב, ve'lo hayah koli
areiv, and it wasn't beautiful anymore. נטלו את תיקונו, natlu et tikuno,
they removed whatever they did to fix it, whatever sort of plating
that they did, והיה קולו ערב כמות שהיה, ve'hayah koli areiv ke'mot
she'hayah, and it was beautiful, right, I don't get it. So maybe
it was, maybe it somehow was chipped, and they wanted to make
it look nicer, but it still made a good sound. Yeah, I
understand the question. We'll read just one more of this. מכתשת היה
במקדש, Machteshet hayah ba'mikdash, they had something that they would use to
grind the spices, yeah, whatever, the fragrances, לפטום הקטורת, le'pitum ha'ketoret, right,
של נחושת היתה, shel nechoshet haytah, copper, מימות משה היתה, mimot Moshe
haytah, this was also passed down from משה, Moshe, והיתה מפטמת את
הבשמים, ve'haytah mepattemet et ha'besamim, they would use it to grind the
fragrances, נתפגמה, nitpagmah, it was damaged somehow, והביאו אומנין מאלכסנדריא של מצרים,
ve'heviu umanin me'Aleksandrya shel Mitzrayim, they brought artisans from Alexandria in Egypt,
ותיקנוה, ve'tiknuah, and they fixed it, ולא היתה מפטמת כמות שהיתה, ve'lo
haytah mepattemet ke'mot she'haytah, it didn't make, right, I mean, it did
not brush it in- weight to release, well it does matter the
way you crush garlic for example, as opposed to, you know, affects
how much it releases its flavor. So it did not release the
same type of aroma. So what did they of course do? כמות
שהיתה, ke'mot she'haytah, נטלו את תיקונה, natlu et tikunah, they removed whatever
they did to fix it, והיתה מפטמת כמות שהיתה. ve'haytah mepattemet ke'mot
she'haytah. Right, so exactly, it still had a מום, mum, but somehow
it was good. Right, there's a very beautiful דרוש drush here. There's
a very beautiful דרוש. drush. Okay, we will continue with this tomorrow.